<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ryotoru.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ryotoru.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-15T23:41:57+00:00</updated><id>https://ryotoru.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CryptiCosmos- Lattice Cryptography and more</title><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Lattices and Learning With Errors</title><link href="https://ryotoru.github.io/blog/2024/math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Lattices and Learning With Errors"/><published>2024-06-17T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ryotoru.github.io/blog/2024/math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ryotoru.github.io/blog/2024/math/"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine waking up one day to find that all your online passwords, secure connections, and encrypted data are suddenly vulnerable. This isn’t the plot of a sci-fi movie – it’s a real concern in the world of cybersecurity. In the world of cryptography, a seismic shift is underway. The looming advent of quantum computers threatens to break many of our current encryption methods, pushing researchers to develop new, quantum-resistant cryptographic systems. At the forefront of this effort are lattice-based cryptographic schemes, with the Learning With Errors (LWE) problem as a cornerstone.</p> <p>In this series of occasional, brief posts, I will be sharing my notes on the topic. Here are some of the topics I plan to cover (hopefully someday!):</p> <ol> <li>[Lattices and their properties]</li> <li>[Hard problems on lattices like SVP, CVP, BDD, GAP versions etc.]</li> <li>[Usage in cryptography]</li> <li>[SIS and LWE]</li> <li>[Worst case to average case reductions (at least classical one)]</li> <li>[Cryptosystems based on LWE]</li> <li>[NIST Candidates]</li> <li>[CRYSTALS suite (at least brief mention of their working)]</li> </ol> <p>From here, two paths emerge: Fully Homomorphic Encryption (FHE), the holy grail of cryptography; or Complexity Theory, exploring why these problems are considered “hard”. Currently, my focus is on FHE.</p> <p>Point to Note: I have been studying lattices since February last year. These blogs are my personal notes and reflections on my understanding so far. Mistakes are inevitable, as learning is a continuous journey. If you spot any inaccuracies or have suggestions, please feel free to educate me. We are all students of this vast and intricate matrix.</p> <p>Before we go further, here is a lattice visualizer tool I made to play around and see the lattice points. Have fun!</p> <iframe src="https://ryotoru.github.io/lattice-visualizer/" width="1024" height="768"></iframe> <h2 id="the-quantum-threat-shors-algorithm">The Quantum Threat: Shor’s Algorithm</h2> <p>In 1994, Peter Shor developed a quantum algorithm that efficiently solves integer factorization and discrete logarithm problems. This breakthrough poses a significant threat to widely used cryptographic protocols:</p> <ol> <li><strong>RSA</strong>: Based on the difficulty of factoring large numbers.</li> <li><strong>Diffie-Hellman key exchange</strong>: Relies on the discrete logarithm problem.</li> <li><strong>Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC)</strong>: The elliptic curve discrete logarithm problem can be solved efficiently.</li> </ol> <p>Once large-scale quantum computers become a reality, these protocols will be effectively broken, compromising much of our current digital security infrastructure.</p> <h2 id="enter-lattices-a-quantum-resistant-foundation">Enter Lattices: A Quantum-Resistant Foundation</h2> <p>This is where lattices come into play. In mathematics, a lattice is a regularly spaced grid of points stretching out to infinity. Imagine a vast checkerboard extending in all directions. These structures turn out to have some fascinating properties that make them excellent building blocks for post-quantum cryptography.</p> <p>To understand lattices mathematically, think of a pattern of points in space that repeats infinitely. Imagine a grid where every point is equally spaced from its neighbors, extending in all directions forever. To describe this mathematically, we need:</p> <ol> <li>A starting point (usually the origin, or (0,0,0) in 3D space)</li> <li>A set of directions that tell us how to move from one point to another</li> </ol> <p>These directions are called “basis vectors”. They’re like the fundamental building blocks of our lattice. Every point in the lattice can be reached by following these directions in different combinations. Here’s a more formal definition: A lattice is the set of all points that can be reached by:</p> <p>a) Starting at the origin b) Moving along the basis vectors c) Using only whole number multiples of these vectors</p> <p>A lattice in \(\mathbb{R}^n\) is formally defined as the set:</p> <p>\(L(b_1, ..., b_n)\) = \(\left\{ \sum_{i=1}^n x_i b_i : x_i \in \mathbb{Z} \right\}\)</p> <p>Where \((b_1, ..., b_n)\) are linearly independent vectors in \(\mathbb{R}^n\).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/A_visual_representation_of_a_lattice_in_a_3-dimens-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/A_visual_representation_of_a_lattice_in_a_3-dimens-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/A_visual_representation_of_a_lattice_in_a_3-dimens-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/A_visual_representation_of_a_lattice_in_a_3-dimens.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A visual representaion of a lattice in a 3-D space. (image generated using Dall-E) </div> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="lattices,"/><category term="post-quantum,"/><category term="cryptography"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A comprehensive introduction to lattice-based cryptography.]]></summary></entry></feed>